<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Functional Transfixity</title>
    <link href="http://blog.mmn80.xyz/atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://blog.mmn80.xyz" />
    <id>http://blog.mmn80.xyz/atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Călin Ardelean</name>
        <email>mmn80cpu@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2016-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Notes about this web site's bowels</title>
    <link href="http://blog.mmn80.xyz/posts/2016-02-23-blog-setup.html" />
    <id>http://blog.mmn80.xyz/posts/2016-02-23-blog-setup.html</id>
    <published>2016-02-23T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div id="contents" class="section level3">
<h3>Contents</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="#static-generator">Static generator</a></li>
<li><a href="#web-theme">Web theme</a></li>
<li><a href="#comments">Comments</a></li>
<li><a href="#tracking-analytics">Tracking &amp; analytics</a></li>
</ul>
</div>
<div id="static-generator" class="section level2">
<h2>Static generator</h2>
<p>Overall I’m quite pleased with <a href="http://jaspervdj.be/hakyll" title="Hakyll">Hakyll</a>, the Haskell <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/" title="Jakyll">Jakyll</a>.</p>
<p>For convenient <a href="https://pages.github.com" title="GitHub Pages">GitHub Pages</a> hosting, you can either keep the sources in the same repo with the output, in which case you’ll need some convoluted scripts to strap it together, or you can figure it’s not worth the bother and just manage a slightly more tedious <a href="https://github.com/mmn80/mmn80.github.io.src" title="Source Repo for this Blog">2</a> - <a href="https://github.com/mmn80/mmn80.github.io" title="Main GitHub Pages Repo">repo</a> setup, like me. After committing changes in the source repo, I run <code>site deploy</code> and then <code>git commit</code> and <code>git push</code> the front repo. I even dig the extra control.</p>
<p><em>Hakyll</em> comes integrated with the mighty, multilingual <a href="http://pandoc.org/README.html" title="Pandoc User’s Guide">pandoc</a>, that champions an enriched <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/" title="Markdown">Markdown</a> dialect I’m delighted to dance with. In particular, you can write paper-like articles, publish them straightforwardly on your blog, and generate alongside a <em>pdf</em> with the <code>pandoc</code> executable, all the while inlining <em>LaTeX</em> for math.</p>
<p>To render the formulas you can pick a standard <em>js</em> service like <em>MathJax</em> or, with the <a href="http://hackage.haskell.org/package/pandoc/docs/Text-Pandoc-Options.html#t:HTMLMathMethod" title="Documentation for pandoc math rendering options"><code>WebTeX</code></a> constructor, a remote image service like <em>Google Chart API</em>, or you can generate math images directly on your server with the <a href="https://hackage.haskell.org/package/latex-formulae-hakyll-0.2.0.1" title="The latex-formulae-hakyll package on Hackage"><strong>latex-formulae-hakyll</strong></a> package, all painless to setup. Currently, the blog employs the <a href="http://hackage.haskell.org/package/pandoc/docs/Text-Pandoc-Options.html#t:HTMLMathMethod" title="Documentation for pandoc math rendering options"><code>MathML</code></a> variant to deliver <em>MathML</em> directly inside the <em>XHTML</em>. Moreover, it injects an icon under the headline (but only if the <em>Markdown</em> source file is explicitly tagged with <code>math</code> in the header section, like this post’s), to encourage readers to use a browser sporting native <em>MathML</em>, like <em>Firefox</em> or <em>Safari</em>.</p>
<p>Here’s a test formula for you: <math display="inline" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mrow><mover><mi>f</mi><mo accent="true">^</mo></mover><mo stretchy="false" form="prefix">(</mo><mi>ξ</mi><mo stretchy="false" form="postfix">)</mo><mo>=</mo><msubsup><mo>∫</mo><mrow><mo>−</mo><mi>∞</mi></mrow><mi>∞</mi></msubsup><mi>f</mi><mo stretchy="false" form="prefix">(</mo><mi>x</mi><mo stretchy="false" form="postfix">)</mo><mspace width="0.222em"></mspace><msup><mi>e</mi><mrow><mo>−</mo><mn>2</mn><mi>π</mi><mi>i</mi><mi>x</mi><mi>ξ</mi></mrow></msup><mspace width="0.167em"></mspace><mi>d</mi><mi>x</mi><mi>.</mi></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">\hat{f}(\xi) = \int_{-\infty}^\infty f(x)\ e^{- 2\pi i x \xi}\,dx.</annotation></semantics></math></p>
</div>
<div id="web-theme" class="section level2">
<h2>Web theme</h2>
<p>I started with the default <em>Hakyll</em> theme but made a few adjustments.</p>
<p>All sizes, including fonts and page width, are relative (in <code>em</code> units). There is also no <code>font-family</code> setting, so the site will use the default fonts on all devices. High-dpi displays won’t collapse the text into a string of microscopic black holes, while on wide screens the need for binoculars and current line markers for navigation will be eschewed.</p>
<p>The black icons are vectorial (<em>SVG</em>), so they look smooth on high-dpi too. With a <em>SVG</em> editor like <a href="https://inkscape.org/en/" title="Inkscape">Inkscape</a> it’s snappy to take some public domain icon from the net (wikipedia has plenty) and delete layers, change colors and sizes, or add your own shapes. The hover effect just uses the <em>CSS3</em> <code>opacity</code> property. I’ll be using <em>SVG</em> for diagrams too.</p>
<p>I followed <a href="http://blog.sigfpe.com/" title="A Neighborhood of Infinity">Dan Piponi</a>‘s example and inlined the <em>archive</em> page into <em>home</em> and <em>contact</em> into the footer. I reckoned the text that would normally go there would be something generic, and surely I’d write more compelling things in the actual blog?!? So why would I pin the trivia? These days, personal info belongs to social networking accounts. And being more honest by placing the index inside <code>index.html</code> should benefit search engine robots’ situational awareness (humans’ too!).</p>
<p>Hope this pasta is plain enough for a copy.</p>
</div>
<div id="comments" class="section level2">
<h2>Comments</h2>
<p>Initially I had a <em>Disqus</em> comments section, but then I read <a href="http://chrisdone.com/posts/blog-comments" title="Comments on my blog - Chris Done">Chris Done’s post</a> and reconsidered.</p>
<p>Indeed, the matter was bothering me since the beginning but couldn’t quite say why. I don’t really buy the “freedom of expression” or “unpopular ideas” framing, but still regard blog comments sections as the worst possible avenue of online debate. Yes, worse then youtube, but let me explain.</p>
<p>First, let’s get out of the way issues like typos and other corrections. E-mail works great for that.</p>
<p>Then there is the problem of ownership, or hosting, in relation to each comment and the discussion as a whole. <em>Disqus</em> deals with the first part, I assume (website disappears, but you keep your, now meaningless, comments), but for people to entrust their effort posts to a host, they need to ascertain its reliability, fairness, and general usefulness. This may involve having good and active moderators, trusting the website won’t drop its back archives due to some natural, financial or legal issue, expecting many dialog-worthy individuals on the same page, etc.</p>
<p>But, due to network effects, it is in the nature of all these things to reinforce each other. Hence, the best places to publicly talk about anything, including blog posts, will always be popular hangouts specifically tuned for this purpose, like <em>reddit</em> and other forums, or community blogs like the <a href="https://golem.ph.utexas.edu/category/" title="The n-Category Café">The n-Category Café</a>, or famous professors’ blogs.</p>
<p>As for the rest of us, if once in a while you write an article whose intent is to provoke debate, you can always post it in such a forum and, if you like, link the forum thread at the back of your article.</p>
</div>
<div id="tracking-analytics" class="section level2">
<h2>Tracking &amp; analytics</h2>
<p>I’m a total hypocrite.</p>
<p>I won’t add much as it should be pretty clear what I mean. This is also why I think confiding private data to governments or corporations is the worst idea ever. They are people like you &amp; me, after all. Well, me, as I don’t know you.</p>
</div>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Pun hazard</title>
    <link href="http://blog.mmn80.xyz/posts/2016-02-22-name.html" />
    <id>http://blog.mmn80.xyz/posts/2016-02-22-name.html</id>
    <published>2016-02-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-02-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div id="welcome-to-the-jungle" class="section level3">
<h3>Welcome to the jungle!</h3>
<p>This is my personal blog on functional programming and its application to real-time simulation. You may expect intermittent pieces on logic <math display="inline" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mo>∩</mo><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">\cap</annotation></semantics></math> math <math display="inline" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><semantics><mo>∩</mo><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">\cap</annotation></semantics></math> physics, and hopefully not too many rants. But ultimately, I have no clue what the blog will end up raving about. For all I know it could spawn enormous Juche pumas playing cylindrical Go along Iapetus’ equatorial ridge, sabotaging the moon’s hydrostatic balance. Worse, I couldn’t seize it a rigid designator, leading to a dangerous pun compromise.</p>
<p>But allow me to waste your time by first elaborating and then, apologizing.</p>
<hr />
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Functional_fixedness" title="Functional fixedness - Wikipedia">Functional fixity</a> is a term from cognitive science describing one’s inability to use an object in a novel way. It’s your memory entangling the representation of the object with that of its intended function, typically after prolonged usage.</p>
<p>For instance, after learning to work a monad to a particular goal, a fledgling Haskeller may feel inclined to blog about what monads are like, promptly forgetting the structure and laws of the mathematical object, a lapse that has little to do, I’ll argue, with the suitability of figurative language for presenting abstract concepts.</p>
<p>Brent Yorgey’s <a href="https://byorgey.wordpress.com/2009/01/12/abstraction-intuition-and-the-monad-tutorial-fallacy/" title="Abstraction, intuition, and the “monad tutorial fallacy”">classic article</a> tells the story of the failed monad tutor who supplies just the root of his intuition and expects the entire tree to magically string along into his reader’s head, confusing, as it were, the pattern used for naming common metaphors (<strong>A is B</strong>), with the metaphors themselves, which are known to develop from elementary inter-domain mappings of arbitrary complexity. The article concludes with a fair advice: play with the abstract concept itself, don’t just get accustomed with more of its incarnations and business roles.</p>
<p>But throughout the story there is an undertone, or potential uncharitable reading, of a rusty grammarian that ’splains: <em>“analogy is bad, m’kay?”</em>. The Haskell community was quick to pick up on it, and confessed they actually <em>take no pickle with <a href="http://blog.plover.com/prog/burritos.html" title="Monads are like burritos - The Universe of Discourse">burrito</a> expositions</em>. And I concur, even outright allegories are fly as long as the mapping maintains a sense of <a href="http://blog.sigfpe.com/2014/05/types-and-two-approaches-to-problem.html" title="Types, and two approaches to problem solving - A Neighborhood of Infinity">faithfulness</a> that allows crisscrossing the domain boundaries without garbling the meaning, and the author doesn’t forget to mention all independent generators of the mapping. I also think that people are pretty good at it, and the confusion Brent’s article poses is a bit of a straw man, as the real problem is not only deeper, but it affects smart, educated people significantly more. I’m talking about functional fixity, a case of <em>“the curse of knowledge”</em>, two concepts I’ve recently been exposed to by Steven Pinker’s wonderful book <a href="http://wadler.blogspot.ro/2016/02/steven-pinkers-sense-of-style.html" title="Steven Pinker&#39;s The Sense of Style - Wadler&#39;s Blog">“The Sense of Style”</a>.</p>
<p>Knowledge is cursed by intelligence. More of the later founds more opportunities for the curse to strike, and intensifies the virulence inside each area. Imagine a cloud-hosted compiler so smart, that it understands your program is socially or economically expandable, and all of it gets eliminated as dead code. You’d have to fight it, politically. Likewise, our extra keen memory will be better at compressing our experience of the <em>path</em> we took to reach it, to a more lucrative, but potentially deceitful arrangement.</p>
<p>But this doesn’t mean our metaphor is somehow fundamentally mangled, rendered useless for teaching, or worse, all metaphors are, and only some thoroughly protestant hard work can make you comprehend anything. On the contrary, the monad tutor is orthodox in believing that <em>“if it works for me, it could help others too”</em>. It’s all a question of first, checking that it actually works, and second, having a consistent &amp; complete rendition, which can be achieved, against the odds brought about by the curse of knowledge, with analogy remodeling and some, well, hard work.</p>
<p>When writing about something, notwithstanding your preference for the <strong>classic style</strong> of exposition, where you speak as if you have something to show and you’re merely guiding the reader towards a <em>better vantage point</em>, you are still essentially creating entirely new knowledge, and should only consider what you already know as one among many aids. But the classic style itself is exactly such an aid, specifically a metaphor, recommended for its efficiency in reducing the bloat caused by, to quote Pinker, “metadiscourse, signposting, hedging, apologizing, professional narcissism, clichés, mixed metaphors, metaconcepts, zombie nouns, and unnecessary passives”.</p>
<p>Rather then wailing destitution, potatoes can be your salvation.</p>
<hr />
<p>Now notice what I’ve did in the previous section. In a narcissistic attempt to justify the pun in the name of the website, I’ve expanded an argument resting solely on a misinterpretation of an article. This is the fundamental moral hazard that figurative language inherits. If you want to be the funny guy but mess up your punch lines, it’s your audience who will first pay the price, and you’ll eventually end up with negative credit.</p>
<p>The safe bet is to use a single, well known, overarching allegory, like the one at the core of the classic style, aka the <em>hitchhiker’s guide</em>. If you also yearn for local boosts, make sure they are connected in a tree of relatedness, with an enforced cost restriction for each descending edge. The payload must be worth the context switch, but it needs not be atomic, just an admix of staggered reimbursements, like in <a href="http://www.cambridge.org/ro/academic/subjects/computer-science/programming-languages-and-applied-logic/purely-functional-data-structures?format=PB&amp;isbn=9780521663502" title="Chris Okasaki - Purely Functional Data Structures">Okasaki’s</a> <em>banker’s method</em>.</p>
<p>I live this cortege of thought here as a testament for future me: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bBu7b1jMUrU" title="I did watch it! The save! - Matt Malone"><em>Watch it!</em></a></p>
</div>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
