<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>Applicative Hazards</title>
        <link>http://clnx.github.io</link>
        <description><![CDATA[Stories on functional programming and the real world]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://clnx.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2016 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Pun Hazards</title>
    <link>http://clnx.github.io/posts/2016-02-12-name.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h2 id="welcome">Welcome!</h2>
<p>This is my personal blog on functional programming and its applications to graphics, physics and distributive computing. There may be occasional posts on logic + math, and hopefully not too many rants.</p>
<p>I couldn’t find a rigid designator for it so I’m going with the lazy pun instead.</p>
<h2 id="hakyll">Hakyll</h2>
<p>Overall I’m very happy with <a href="http://jaspervdj.be/hakyll" title="Hakyll">Hakyll</a>. I think this <a href="https://github.com/clnx/clnx.github.io.src" title="Source Repo for this Blog">2</a> - <a href="https://github.com/clnx/clnx.github.io" title="Main GitHub Pages Repo">repo</a> setup is the easiest to work with on <a href="https://pages.github.com" title="GitHub Pages">GitHub Pages</a>. I stole some code from <a href="http://jozefg.bitbucket.org/" title="Code &amp; Co">Danny Gratzer’s blog</a> to get me started, but I got going quickly.</p>
<h2 id="css-theme">CSS Theme</h2>
<p>I started with the default <code>Hakyll</code> theme but made a few adjustments.</p>
<p>All sizes, including fonts and page width, are relative (in <code>em</code> units). There is also no <code>font-family</code> setting, so the site will use the default fonts on all devices. Especially on high-dpi screens your eyes won’t be strained by the microscopic fixed text that so many sport, while on wide screens you won’t need binoculars and current line markers to navigate.</p>
<p>The black icons are vectorial (<em>SVG</em>), so they look good on high-dpi too. With a <em>SVG</em> editor like <a href="https://inkscape.org/en/" title="Inkscape">Inkscape</a> it’s very fast to take some free icon from the net and delete layers, change colors and sizes, or make your own. The hover effect just uses the <em>CSS3</em> <code>opacity</code> property.</p>
<p>Hope this pasta is simple enough for a copy.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2016 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://clnx.github.io/posts/2016-02-12-name.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Călin Ardelean</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
